[MUSIC]
So now that we've seen Intents,
let's talk about how you use
Intents to start activities.
Now, if you remember
back to the last lesson,
I talked about how you can problematically
start an activity using methods such as
startActivity or, startActivityForResult.
Now, when you use one of these methods,
Android has to figure out which single
activity it's going to start up.
And there are two ways in
which Android does this.
The first way is that if you explicitly
named the target activity when you created
the intent then Android can just look
that up and start that specific activity.
The second way which is only used
if you haven't explicitly set
the target activity,
is that Android can implicitly determine
it based on the intent that was used and
based on the properties of activities
that you have installed on your device.
So let's take a look at an application
that explicitly starts another activity.
And this application is called
Hello World With Login.
And it's comprised of two activities.
There's one activity called LoginActivity.
And another called HelloAndroid.
Now when this application launches,
LoginActivity is the first
activity that's started.
LoginActivity provides a textbox for
typing a username and another one for
entering a password.
There is also a button and
once the user enters their username and
password, they'll hit the Login button.
And then LoginActivity will check
the entered pass, password and username.
And if it accepts them, it will then
start the HelloAndroid activity,
which will then display
the words HelloAndroid.
Let's see that in action.
So here's my device.
I'll go to the home screen.
And then I launch the HelloAndroid
with Login application.
This pops up a user interface screen,
allowing me to enter a user name and
a password.
Now enter that information.
And now that I'm done,
I'll click the Login button.
If LoginActivity accepts my user name and
password, then another activity starts
displaying the words, HelloAndroid.
So let's look at the code to see
exactly how this is implemented.
I'll start by opening up
a LoginActivity class.
Here I'm showing a listener code
that's attached to the Login button.
And here, the code grabs the username and
password that the user
has just entered, and then passes them
to a method called checkPassword.
If checkPassword returns true,
then the code will continue.
First it creates an intent
called hello intent,
and as you can see the call to the intent
constructor takes two parameters,
a context and a class object for
the activity to be started.
In this case LoginActivity.this
is used as the context.
Now a context is an interface that's used
to access global application information.
And since activity is
a sub class of context,
it's fine to use LoginActivity.this for
this parameter.
The second parameter is the class object.
In this case, for
the HelloAndroidActivity.
This parameter indicates the activity to
be started by the call to start activity.
The second way to start an activity
is by implicit activation.
In this situation you haven't told
Android which activity to start so
it has to figure it out on it's own.
And what happens here is that Android
tries to match the intent that was
passed in to start activity,
or start activity for
result with the capabilities of
activities that are on your device.
And this process is
called intent resolution.
Intent resolution relies on
two kinds of information.
First, there's the intent that
the calling activity created to
describe the operation that
it wants to be performed.
And second,.
Individual Android activities
specify intent filters
which describe the kinds of operations or
intents that they can handle.
And this information is usually placed
in the AndroidManifest.XML file,
or the applications to which
the activities belong.
At run time when the start activity
run method is actually called,
Android will try to match the intent with
the intent filters that it knows about.
However, it's only going to use part
of the intent information when it
does this matching.
Specifically, it will
look at the Action field.
He will look at the Data; including
both the URI and the mime type.
And he will look at the Category.
So let's take a look at how applications
specify IntentFilters within their
androidmanifest.xml files.
So here's an XML snippet showing
an activity tag and this activity tag
includes within it an intent
filter tag,that intent filter tag
includes within it an action corresponding
to the intent action that it can support.
For example.
If an activity can dial phone numbers,
then it
should include an intent filter with
the standard action, intent.action_dial.
Now that's the, the Java name for that.
The actual value is, is really a string.
So you'll see andriod.intent.action.dial.
That's the value that will actually
be written into the intent filter.
If your activity handles
a specific type of data,
it can add that information to
its intent filter as well, for
example, an activity can specify
the mime type of the data it handles.
You can also specify the scheme, host and
or port number of the data UIs it handles.
It can further limit the format of
the data URI by specifying it's path,
pathPattern or pathPrefix.
And there are quite a few possibilities
here, so please see the documentation for
more examples.
Now, if an activity wants to
publish that it can show maps for
example, then it might include
an intent filter, like this one,
which tells Android that it can handle
data URIs that have a geo scheme.
Similarly, activities can specify
categories for the intents they handle.
And let's look at an example
that puts all of this together.
Now, we can guess or
imagine based on those map location
applications we saw before,
that Google Maps can handle intents that
have an action of intent.action_view.
And that have a data field
with the geo scheme.
Now a while back I decided to take a look
at the Android manifest.xml file for
the Google maps application.
And what I saw looked something like this.
There was an activity
with an intent filter.
And that intent filter listed
in action of intent action.view.
And it had data, had a data scheme of geo.
In fact, this is exactly what the map
location applications passed into start
activity So going back to Google maps,
the activity also listed two categories.
Category.browsable meaning
that it can respond to
browser links and cateogry.default.
Now it turns out that in most
cases activities that want to ac,
accept implicit intents, must include
category.defualt in their intent filters.
Finally when more than one activity
can accept a particular intent,
Android will have to break
the tie in some way.
And one way to do that is just to
ask the user which activity, he or
she wants to handle the intent and
you may have seen that.
Another possibility is that
activities can specify a priority.
That Android will take into
account when deciding between,
two different activities that
can handle a particular intent.
Now those priority values should be
between, minus 1000 and positive 1000.
And higher values, mean higher priority.
Now for those of you who are interested
in knowing more about intent filters,
I recommend you take a look
at the adb dumpsys command.
Here I've opened up a terminal window.
And now I'll issue the command
adb shell dumpsys package.
Now this is going to spit out a ton of
information from the package manager.
So I'll just capture the output of
this command in to a text file.
Let's run the command.
And now I'll open that
file in a text editor.
I'll use emacs and
then we'll search for the string geo.
And what you're seeing here is that
the Google Maps application in
fact has an intent filter for
URI's with the geo scheme.